As you can see, the receiver itself is pretty
simple. Extend the broadcast receiver class and override the
onreceive handle as you can see here. Receivers are
lightweight components meant to listen for broadcasts, reacts, and complete
within five seconds that usually means simply starting a
service or sending a notification. To have your receiver
start listening for broadcasts, you need to register it
either through an entry in your manifest like this or
dynamically within another application component usually an activity,
like this. Then you define the intent filter that
specifies the broadcast event you want to receive.
You can do that either here in the manifest
or if you're registering your receiver with an
application component such as an activity, you can create
your new intent filter like this. The biggest difference
between manifest and dynamic receivers is when they're triggered.
A programmatically-registered receiver will only receive broadcasts while
the app is running. While a manifest declared
receiver will start your app specifically to receive
your broadcasts. For example, I usually code with
my noise cancelling headphones on, so a music
app like this might want to register a runtime
receiver to listen to the system intent broadcast
that announces when headphones are unplugged. That will allow
it to automatically pause playback, when your audio routing switches
from headphone to speakers. In this case, we can use
a runtime receiver, because the app is guaranteed to be
running if music is playing. On the other hand, if I'm
using Google Cloud Messaging to listen for new data from
my server, I want to register a manifest receiver that always listens
for incoming tickles from my server and will wake up
my app if it's being terminated to trigger the update code,
usually a sync adapter, which is something we will discuss
later in lesson six. There's a bunch of system broadcasts
you can monitor to help your app react to changes
in the system. You can see the system broadcast actions within
the intent documentation at developer.android.com. One great use for broadcast
receivers is to monitor for changes to internet connectivity or
charging status. Imagine your app has to upload a movie
or calculate the next 10,000 moves in a game of chess,
how might you use a receiver to wait until the device is plugged in
before starting that process? Should it be
a manifest receiver or a broadcast receiver?